Michael Mateta

Email: michaeljeibc@outlook.com | Mobile: 07748248648 | Location: Remote, Leeds & Wakefield

LinkedIn: linkedIn: linkedin.com/in/michael-mateta-033327b3

PROFILE

A Digital Solutions Architect with Microsoft Certifications in Data Engineering and Power BI Analysis. I have worked as a Senior SQL BI Developer for 10 years then became a Data Engineer in Azure Cloud solutions before now being a Solutions Architect. A strategist, who understands business needs and delivers `full-cycle` projects; capturing and analysing requirements, whilst supporting effective communication and an optimised delivery. Thrives at the interface between the business and technical world; transforming requirements into technical specifications and explaining possibilities in clear, simple terms. Team focussed, with valuable problem solving skills and the ability to engage with stakeholders at all levels to ensure needs are identified and fully addressed. Technically experienced in current and emerging technologies and focussed on today's and tomorrow's technical priorities, including in Cloud Architecture, Database Development, Data Modelling Design, Test Driven Development and Analysis, Azure Databricks, Data Factory, DevOps and SQL Server.

KEY SKILLS

- Analysis and evaluation
- Analytical Thinker
- Building/leading effective teams
- Change Management
- Client relationship management
- Commercial and business acumen
- Complex Problem Solving
- Compliance / Governance
- Corporate and social responsibilities •
- Creative and innovative approach
- Customer focused
- Customer Service

- Flexible and Adaptable Approach
- Influencing and motivating
- IT and technical skills
- Management and leadership
- Managing budgets and financials
- Market research and analysis
- Organisation and Planning
- Process and System Improvement
 - **Product Management**
- Project Delivery
- Relationship Management
- Risk Management and Mitigation

- Sales and business development
- Stakeholder Management
- Operational Planning
- Strategic partnerships
- Strong problem-solving ability
- Sustainable growth management
- Target and Timescale driven
- Teamwork and collaboration
- Thrives under pressure
- Time and resource management
- Training / Mentoring / Coaching
- Training and development

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Digital Solutions Architect – Ipsos Karian and Box (Contract)

2022 – Current

- An Azure Data Solutions Architect responsible for systems architecture within the Digital Solutions team, designing and developing strong robust systems for client survey projects and the framework lookup.
- Working collaboratively with team of Managing and Client Directors, Data Engineers and Developers to provide system solutions based on gathered and fully thought through business requirements.
- Scrum Master facilitating Sprint morning stand-ups, backlog refinement sprint planning and Sprint reviews
 and Retrospectives. Supporting the Product Owner and Development Manager to ensure the backlog is
 groomed and stories are ready for sprint planning.
- Mentoring and leading team of Data Engineers and helping keep the team aligned toward key outcomes managing day to day data platform delivery of each sprint of the Scrum team.
- Cloud computing, Database Administration and data architecture using Microsoft. Projects include Survey Specification Definition, Framework lookup tool in Azure Databricks, Azure SQL, Azure Data Lake and ADF.

• Building a POC Delta Lakehouse in Databricks to help the business load and manage large survey data volumes for global benchmarking and survey framework comparison analysis using Spark and SQL.

Azure DevOps Data Engineer - Costain

2021 - 2022

- Working with Costain's DevOps team as a Data Developer and Engineer using my expertise within Microsoft's SQL Azure / Data Factory / PowerBi platforms to play a pivotal part in architecting, developing, managing, and supporting Costain's Enterprise Data Warehouse.
- Building Data Infrastructure for Carbon Emission reductions project and the Carbon BIM project for Costain to be a more governed and globally environmental responsible company.
- Helping ensure the EDW team is kept up to date with the rapid growth of Costain's digital transformation by maintaining accuracy, support and management of the Enterprise Data Warehouse.
- Experience in Data Engineering and Architecture. Managing open sourced ADF orchestrator framework that allows pipelines for EDW data to run correctly in the right order restarting when failed and managed by the JSON metadata behind it.
- Maintaining the EDW wiki for technical aspects in the Data team to be easily referred to at any time and explanation of technical process for business users unfamiliar with code sets managed. Wiki is also good for troubleshooting and investigations for time reduction in recurrences.

Technical Lead – Metro Bank (Contract)

2020 - 2021

- Working in a Financial Services organization building complex data solutions using enterprise SQL Server
 2016 for regulatory reporting building SSIS packages and designing SQL Data marts.
- Designed and built SSIS Framework which is an automated tool that sequences and runs all the SQL Agent jobs within the Database team to manage all the data marts and business reports.
- Working on Azure Data Factory Framework to manage data loads from Azure Data Lake and other nonrelational data sources into the Azure SQL Databases for the Enterprise Data Warehouse development project
- Troubleshooting failing Stored procedures, and long running queries made by other developers and contractors who worked for Metro Bank, replacing the code with better performing indexed views and rewriting or fixing broken stored procedures to make them simpler and re-usable.

Senior Database Developer – Lowell Financial

2015 - 2020

- Built Azure DevOps Pipelines for Database and ADF releases, CI, CD and policy management for releases
- Built Azure Data Factory pipelines for loading of external data into Datawarehouse reporting Data Marts
- Data warehousing of customer data from different transaction databases into one central EDW
- SQL and SSIS development projects included Application Simplification, Design and Migration of CCA Statements into a new more updated more robust processes using Test Driven Development.
- Helped increase the level of support and knowledge of key systems through cross training and reduction in single person dependencies with teams and team members such as Application Support and the SQL team.

Senior Database Developer and Team Lead – More2 Ltd, London

2010 - 2015

- Core tasks include building new and maintaining client related databases, delivery of database projects and analysis based on business requirements, designing campaign outputs, data cleansing and ETL processing.
- Built and maintain SSISWWETL scripts to extract and transform data to business applications whilst fully taking technical ownership of client marketing databases and responsibility for my team. Developed and maintained ETL processes (SSIS), BI and analysis (T-SQL, SSIS and SSRS) whilst providing 2nd line support.
- Liaising closely with the CRM and Client Strategy team to maintain/improve client service levels
- Consistently performed high data quality checks on my work and of other team members
- Adherence to coding standards, and quality assurance policies and procedures

EDUCATION AND SYSTEMS EXPERTISE

2022
2022
2021
2021
2021
2021
2020
2019
2015
2012

TSQL and Programming skills – Gained extensive hands-on experience in scripting T-SQL in constructing triggers, tables, user functions, views, indexes, user profiles, relational database models, data dictionaries, and data integrity, optimized indexes, and statistics in relation to reporting model. Used partition function to create partition tables and partitioned Indexes.

Computer Systems Engineering BEng – Cardiff University Wales UK

2008

Professional Skills – Microsoft technology stack, implementation of client/server, database applications and reporting models using Microsoft SQL Server, SSIS, SSRS, ETL, Azure DevOps, Azure Data Factory, Azure Databricks, Python, Spark, Delta Lake and Visual Studio. Test-First Unit Testing Database and SSIS Package Development. I am an expert in Microsoft SQL Server Agent designing and creating system jobs the transform business requirements into fully functioning technical data solutions.

Training in –Azure SQL Administrator, Azure Administrator and Azure DevOps Certification, Kubernetes, Docker, Solutions Architecture and AI Engineering all for *2023* Certifications